A Guide to the Papers of Henry Clay, 1798-1934, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series I: Correspondence and Documents
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to B.[ellamy] Storer 1834 August 8, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked Lexington Aug.26. #2148. (Box-folder 2:3)
    Clay is eager to hear the election results from Ohio. He says "the Jackson party has been annihilated" in Kentucky. He concludes with a discussion of the charter of the Bank of the United States.
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to B.[enjamin] W.[atkins] Leigh 1834 August 24, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked Lexington Aug.26. #1395. (Box-folder 2:4)
    Clay asks Leigh to "investigate thoroughly at Richmond the subject of Scrip-warrants and come back to the Senate with such information as will enable us...to secure the Government against frauds." Clay says that the result of "our recent Elections " in Kentucky "put us at ease" and says that Whigs in Indiana, Illinois and Missouri also did well. Clay then asks if "any thing can be more stupid than the course of Duff Green?" Clay says he is convinced Green's true purpose is "to affect the election of Mr. V. Buren." Clay closes with a comment on the precarious nature of his wife's health.
  - Henry Clay, to Hamilton Smith 1834 September 6, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked Lexington [Sep.?] 9; docketed; Barrow. #5421. (Box-folder 2:4)
    Clay replies to Smith's query "regarding my opinion whether the manufacturing business, and especially that of cottn may be expected to revive." Clay say that much depends on "certain great elections at hand in Penna [Pennsylvania] and elsewhere." If these elections are favorable to the current administration, Clay says "we may expect for some time to come a continuance of the derangement of the currency, exchange, etc. with all train of consequences."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to B.[enjamin] W.[atkins] Leigh 1834 October 22, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed. #1403. (Box-folder 2:5)
    Clay asks for the address of Mr. Johnson for a neighbor who wishes to write to him. Clay states that "Ohio has acquitted herself nobly. [James] Findlay is supposed to be elected by several thousand, and four or five Jackson members of the H. of R. have been made to yield their places to Whigs."
  - Henry Clay, Senate Chamber, to H.[enry] Shaw 1835 February 4, ALS, 1 p.; with attached blank leaf; with ALS, H.W. Shaw, New York, to Dear Baldwin, 1875 June 15. #1754-b. (Box-folder 2:6)
    Clay expresses confidence in Shaw's "continued friendship." He adds that he regrets "extremely to hear of the distractions which you describe as prevailing among the Whigs in Massachusetts & sincerely hope that they may be finally brought to harmonize together." The letter from Shaw (written below Clay's letter) to Baldwin transmits the letter as a gift for his "extensive and valuable collection of autograph letters."
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to Mrs. Mayard C. Meade 1835 December 18, ALS, 1 p. #1769. (Box-folder 2:7)
    Clay has received Mrs. Meade's letter with the papers she sent for Judge Parker. He has given the papers to Parker who will review them after which "he will present them to the Senate, and move their reference to a Committee. We have talked of that on Foreign Relations."
  - [Henry Clay] to John Wickham 1836 January 23, AN, 1 p.; signature excised. #15753. (Box-folder 2:7a)
    Clay introduces Mr. Bainbridge of Kentucky.
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to John Harvie 1836 February 11, ALS, 1 p. #2196. (Box-folder 2:8)
    Clay introduces Richard D. Cutts, "the son of a particular friend of mine, and the nephew of Mrs. Madison and Mrs. Todd."
  - Henry Clay, Senate Chamber, to A.[lfred] Beckley 1836 May 10, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked Washington May 10. #10012. (Box-folder 2:9)
    Clay says that he will "be happy to furnish you with any Durham Cattle, or other stock in my possession which you may want." He suggests Beckley come to Ashland and select the stock himself. Clay closes by saying that he has "been a long time in public life, and think I may shortly retire without being liable to any reproach for leaving it."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to Dr. Conway D. Whittle 1836 August 6, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington Aug.8. #7973. (Box-folder 2:10)
    Clay acknowledges Whittle's letter of July 13th and says he would have answered it sooner if he "could have communicated the information you wish to possess." Clay wrote to "Col. Edm. H. Taylor" who is "well informed in regard to lands and persons situated where your land lies." Col. Taylor's enclosed response [not present] indicates he is not familiar with Whittle's land and Clay suggests that Whittle "open a correspondence" with Taylor.
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to A.[lexander] W. Stow 1837 April 26, ALS, 2 pp.; with attached address leaf. #991, Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box-folder 2:11)
    Clay comments on Stow's health and sends wishes for "a speedy and effectual recovery." Clay then discusses the institution of slavery and says it "is an institution of which our Country would be most happily rid of, if it were practicable." "In spite of the delusions of those who are directly interested in its preservation, and of the rash and impolitic interference of those who have no direct interest and no right to interfere about it, undoubtedly it is fraught with great mischiefs to both races, to say nothing of the injustice which it inflicts upon one of them." Separation of the races, "by first Colonizing the free blacks and afterwards with the consent of the Slave States, the class of slaves," is the only practical solution. Clay then comments on the country's "Commercial embarrassment" and mentions a reduction in the price of cotton. "The measures of Government have beyond all doubt contributed largely to produce the present calamitous state of affairs."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to Alexander Hamilton 1837 May 26, ALS, 1 p.; with attached blank leaf. #2583. (Box-folder 2:12)
    Clay thanks Hamilton for the "Caricature" that he sent. Clay will make a statement in Congress about the "present unhappy state of our Country." Mr. [Daniel] Webster and his family left Lexington yesterday after a week-long visit. Clay concludes with a postscript stating that he has "heard that suspension of Specie payments by the Banks in the West is general, without a single exception."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to R.[obert] P.[erkins] Letcher 1837 August 5, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington Aug.7, overwritten as 8. #5039. (Box-folder 2:13)
    Clay declines Letcher's invitation "to take the excursion to Lancaster" since he is leaving for Washington shortly. He would like to see Letcher at Ashland to let him know "what has been done, and is doing, about bringing me out as a Candidate." Clay has "given no consent for the use of my name; and shall hesitate much before I do."
  - Henry Clay, S.[enate] Chamber, to W.[illiam] O. Niles 1837 September 27, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed. #3758. (Box-folder 2:14)
    Clay replies to Niles' note and tells him "that not one step is yet taken towards the preparation of the Speech, which I pronounced on Monday."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to M.[atthew] L. Davis 1837 October 30, ALS, 1 p. #4925. (Box-folder 2:15)
    Clay thanks Davis for his letter "communicating the arrangements which have been made, in the City of New York, for the approaching Election to the Legislature." Clay would like to know the results. He states that the "opposition in the West is firm, increasing and unconquerable" and that "Ohio has fulfilled our hopes."
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to Saml. I. Peters 1838 January 9, ALS, 1 p.; with attached blank leaf. #1754-b. (Box-folder 2:16)
    Clay states that "it is not my general habit to acknowledge Pamphlets" that are sent to him but he cannot "deny myself the pleasure of expressing my thanks" for the pamphlet by the Chamber of Commerce of New Orleans sent by Peters.
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to John Agg 1838 May 4, LS, 1 p.; in an unidentified hand, signed by Clay; ghost of another ALS on verso. #1754-b. (Box-folder 2:17)
    Clay thanks Agg for his note and says that he has "nothing whatever to do" with the "new paper" Agg mentions. Clay says that "our political friends" have long contemplated establishing another paper in Washington. Clay understands that "Mr. [William D.] Merrick" and "Mr. [Rice] Garland are two of the Committee charged with attending to that business."
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to F.[ortescue] Whittle 1838 May 15, ALS, 1 p. #7973. (Box-folder 2:18)
    Clay thanks Whittle for his friendly letters. He says that those who "like you and I, have been for a long time deploring the infatuation and delusion which have sustained, so unfortunately, Genl. Jackson in his reckless course have much reason to rejoice in the prospects of better and brighter times which are opening upon us." Clay hopes to see "our Government once more confided to honest and faithful hands" but whether he will "be called to the station or not...is a subordinate concern."
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to J.[ohn] M.[iddleton] Clayton 1838 June 15, ALS, 1 p.; silked. #4948. (Box-folder 2:19)
    Clay thanks Clayton for his letter and says he has "been always proud of the attachment and confidence of your noble State." Clay says that Delaware has exhibited "an encouraging moral spectacle...throughout all these times of trouble" and that the courage and constancy of Delaware is "worthy of the best days of Greece and Rome." Clay thinks that, "in regard to the next Presidency...[d]ivision is weakness, as Union is strength." He closes with a comment on the sub-treasury bill, which he hopes will be defeated.
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to M.E. Pointois 1838 July 2, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. #3121. (Box-folder 2:20)
    Clay introduces Felix Huston, "Commander of the Texan Armies."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to N.[athan] Sargent 1838 August 11, ALS, 2 pp.; with attached blank leaf. #991, Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box-folder 2:21)
    Clay acknowledges Sargent's letter and says he shares the "feelings excited by the bright and encouraging prospects which have opened on our public affairs." Clay says that they "have not yet overcome all difficulties; the adversary is in possession of the field." If the elections in New York and Pennsylvania result in Whig success, Clay foresees an end "to the whole controversy." Clay is pleased with Whig successes in the Kentucky elections but is anxious about the results in Illinois and Missouri.
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to C.C. Baldwin 1838 August 28, ALS, 3 pp.; negative photostat; location of original unknown. #3417-a. (Box-folder 2:22)
    Clay tells Baldwin that in regards to slavery, the tariff and internal improvement, he expressed himself "as fully and as explicitly as language can admit of during the last Session of the Senate of the U.S." Clay says that the slave states "have exclusive power" over the institution; that "Congress has no power touching the institution" and further has "no power to prevent the removal of slaves from one Slave State to another;" and, finally, that Congress cannot abolish slavery "in the D. of Columbia or in the territories, without a violation of good faith." Clay states that he supports a "bill to distribute among the States the proceeds of the public lands" for internal improvements. He supports the Bank of the United States "for the benefits of the institution," but is unconcerned about its location. Clay tells Baldwin that he cannot consent to the publication of this letter. He mentions that the voters of Kentucky have voted down a proposed convention, which was supported "principally by Van Buren men." He tells Baldwin that he is not "a friend to Slavery" and that it is "an evil." However, Clay believes "it better that Slaves should remain Slaves than be set loose as free men among us." Such Clay says was the belief of "our Revolutionary ancestors." The current defense that "Slavery is a blessing" is "espoused by the new school in South Carolina." Clay says that if this is true "the more of it the better; and it is immaterial upon that hypothesis, whether the slaves be black or white." Clay concludes that he is not a candidate for the Presidency and that to speak on the use of the veto by the President would be improper.
  - Henry Clay and Mackenzie Beverly, [Fredericksburg?], to John Minor 1838 November 20, L, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked Fredericksburg Nov. 20. #3750. (Box-folder 2:23)
    In Beverly's hand? Beverly and Clay ask Minor to collect the "bond for my smith...take out for fees & forward the amount through the bank." Minor is then asked to provide a pass for Richard "a few days before xmas" to "come over and see if you can hire him in the next year & have his hire paid quarterly if practical." Richard might require $2.00 "to bring himself home" and Minor is asked to get the amount from Richard's employer and "see if he is well shod and clothed."
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to G.[eorge] W. Featherstonhaugh 1839 February 10, ALS 2 pp.; with attached blank leaf and separate address leaf; docketed; postmarked Washington Feb. 11.; with typed transcription. #6004. (Box-folder 2:24)
    Clay assures Featherstonhaugh that he has not said anything to "Mr. [Louis Joseph] Papineau" about British-Canadian relations that he has not said to British officials. Clay said that the United States "would not interfere, on Canadian account, and never but as a collateral affair, when they might happen to be engaged, on their own proper account, in a contest with G. Britain." Clay says that he is eager "to cultivate & preserve the most friendly relations" with Great Britain and not to interfere in "the contest between the parent Country & the Colony."
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to Horace Greeley 1839 February 11, ALS, 1 p. #10751. (Box-folder 2:25)
    Clay believes that Greeley's proposed pamphlet on the public lands "will be attended with excellent effect." Clay is unable to supply the documents Greeley requested and tells him they have been published in Niles' Register.
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to J.[oseph] R. Ingersoll 1839 June 24, ALS, 1 p.; with attached blank leaf; docketed. #3920. (Box-folder 2:26)
    Clay thanks Ingersoll for his letter and tells him it "brought me the first authentic intelligence of the Chambersburg Convention." Clay thinks that "Anti-Masonry, however right its votaries may be, can never become the basis of the politics of this whole Union." Clay expects to leave "next week on an excursion to the Lakes, the Falls of Niagara and Canada, neither of which I have yet seen." He dreads the possibility of "parade or demonstrations on my account." Clay mentions "Judge Wooley" [Aaron K. Woolley], Horace Binney, John Sergeant, and Josiah Randall.
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to B.[enjamin] W.[atkins] Leigh 1839 September 25, ALS, 2 pp.; with attached blank leaf; docketed. #1403. (Box-folder 2:27)
    Clay thanks Leigh for his letter and encloses "two letters from Genl. Harrison" [not present]. Clay says Harrison "counts confidently upon receiving the nomination." Clay then comments extensively on election prospects in New York, Maryland, Tennessee, and Indiana. Clay says that several of the "new States have rushed prematurely and unwisely" into expensive programs of internal improvements, for which they have had to borrow funds. The Jackson party, which initially supported the programs "turns round & opposes them, and endeavors to the lay the blame at the door of the Whigs!" Clay closes by asking if any political party ever existed "which equals it in inconsistency?"
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to William Tompkins 1839 October 12, ALS, 2 pp.; with attached blank leaf; docketed. #9521. (Box-folder 2:28)
    "Confidential" in Clay's hand at top of p. 1. Clay tells Tompkins that he received a letter from "Genl. Harrison" in response to the letter he sent "on my passage through Ohio." Harrison's letter was "written in the most friendly spirit" and stated that he "had never desired to be thrown into a competition with me, whose election he had desired." Harrison's letter "does not say, in terms, that he will abide by the nomination of the Convention, but that is to be inferred from the fervor of the letter." Clay comments on elections in New York and questions how the "Administration party" has been able to make gains. He says that "the Administration has put its hands, in its desperation, into the public treasury, and taken out hundreds of thousands of dollars to use in purposes of corruption." Clay says that he fears his prediction that "Jackson ruled by intimidation and V. Buren would by corruption" has come true. Clay comments on the "Staunton Convention" and hopes it will arouse the people of Virginia "to a due sense of the dangers which encompass them." Clay closes with comments on the elections in Tennessee and voter fraud in Alabama.
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to N.[athan] Sargent 1839 October 25, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked Oct.26. #991, Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box-folder 2:29)
    Clay thanks Sargent for "communicating the results of the Election in the City and County of Philadelphia. He comments on the elections in Pennsylvania, New York and Massachusetts and says he is "grieved to witness the divisions among the Whigs." Clay says he would consent to have his name withheld at the "Harrisburg Convention" if doing so would increase the Whig Party's chances of success.
  - Henry Clay, S.[enate] Chamber, to John L. Carey 1840 January 7, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Washington Jan.7. #3920. (Box-folder 2:30)
    Clay thanks Carey for sending a copy of the second edition of his pamphlet Some thoughts on domestic slavery. Clay is pleased that Carey also sent copies to "Mr. [Franck] Taylor," a Washington bookseller.
  - Henry Clay and J.J. Crittenden, Washington, to The Honble Secy of War 1840 March 25, ALS, 1 p. #2290, Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box-folder 2:31)
    Clay and Crittenden transmit to Joel Roberts Poinsett a letter from the Governor of Kentucky "containing evidence of the application of a quantity of arms belonging to that State to the use of the United States." Clay and Crittenden ask if the arms can be replaced "in a course of administration, without a special act of Congress."
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to William Coffin 1840 March 28, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Washington Mar. 28. #1754-b. (Box-folder 2:32)
    Clay thanks Coffin for sending "to Copies of my engraved likeness."
  - Henry Clay to Mr. Onderdonk 1840 April 29, ANS, 1 p. #1754-b. (Box-folder 2:33)
    Clay sends Onderdonk a copy of one of the speeches he requested. Clay notes that the "others are to be found in the periodicals of the day."
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to J.[ohn] M. Clayton [1840 May 8], ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked May 8. #2933. (Box-folder 2:34)
    Clay is "grieved" to hear of Clayton's accident and says he considers himself "the cause, although the innocent cause of it." If Clay had been well enough to visit Clayton in New Castle it "would not have happened." Clay hopes to be well enough "to make tomorrow my excursion to Philad." and will visit Clayton while there or on his return to Washington.
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to Danl. [Daniel] Gardner 1840 July 7, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked Washington Jul.7. #2291, Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box-folder 2:35)
    Clay apologizes that he lacks the time to respond fully to Gardner's letter. Clay's thoughts "may be found in the Panama instructions" which were published in Niles' Register and the "State Papers of Congress."
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to Messrs. McNairy, Hall, Marcy?, Huston, Manlove & Norvell 1840 July 10, ALS, 1 p. #1761. (Box-folder 2:36)
    Clay thanks the men for their invitation to visit Nashville on August 17, but says that he is "worn down by the fatigues of an exhausting Session of Congress" and cannot come so soon. He suggests a later visit in either September or October.
  - Henry Clay, S.[enate] Chamber, to S. Lawrence 1840 July 11, ALS, 1 p. #1754-b. (Box-folder 2:37)
    Clay introduces G.W. Brown of Charleston, S.C. "who is desirous of viewing the Northern manufactories."
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to Charles F. Mayer 1840 December 8, ALS, 1 p. #3121. (Box-folder 2:38)
    Clay tells Mayer that he is well acquainted with "our friend D.[avid] Hoffman" but since Clay has "no expectation of being otherwise connected with the new administration than as a member of the Senate," he is unable to aid Hoffman.
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to J. Trotter 1841 February 8, ALS, 1 p. with attached address leaf. #2908. (Box-folder 2:39)
    Clay encloses a draft for $2575 [not present] "for collection and to be put to my account in Bank." Clay tells Trotter that before the "recent suspension, and whilst your Bank was paying Specie" he drew a check for $2000 and sent it to Kentucky. Clay hopes there will be no problem paying the check "in Greens, or lawful currency."
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to [unidentified recipient] 1841 March 15, ALS, 1 p.; with attached blank leaf; name of recipient clipped out. #3920. (Box-folder 2:40)
    Clay thanks the recipient for the "box containing the Shirts and Stocks" and sends his thanks to "Mrs. P[ ]er?" as well. Clay will deliver the recipient's message to General Harrison when he next sees him and "would send him one of the shirts but that I know it will not fit him."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to James F. Conover 1841 April 9, ALS, 1 p.; with attached blank leaf and separate address leaf; docketed; postmarked Lexington. #4475. (Box-folder 2:41)
    Clay says that "the distressing intelligence of the death of Genl. Harrison" has reached him and that it is "greatly to be deplored, although it does not surprize me much, from what I observed of his habits and excitement." Clay declines a suggestion to deliver a eulogy for Harrison on the grounds of the "yet feeble state of my strength." Clay is sorry that Conover was unable to obtain an appointment in Washington and says that he has "no power, not the bestowal of a single office." Clay concludes by stating that "V.P. Tyler will, I presume, not confine the patronage of the Govt. exclusively to any particular class of Whigs."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to Jno. [John] L. Lawrence 1841 April 13, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington Apr.15; silked. #5828-a. (Box-folder 2:42)
    Clay shares Conover's "surprize and regret" about William Henry Harrison's death. He states that he has known Vice President Tyler "long and intimately" and that he "has ability quite equal to his predecessor, is amiable, and I think honest and patriotic. His defect is want of moral firmness." Clay says that he believes the member of the Cabinet should have resigned on Harrison's death.
  - John Tyler, Washington, to Henry Clay 1841 April 30, ALS, 4 pp.; docketed; silked. #2362. (Box-folder 2:43)